Here's an example of that.
سأعطيكم مثال على ذلك.
I was once working for a large client with offices in more than one country.
عملت ذات مرة مع عميل كبير، وشركته لها عدة مكاتب في أكثر من دولة.
I was working on a module,
كنت أعمل على نموذج
which needed some significant data from another stakeholder within the same organization.
يتطلب بيانات هامة من صاحب مصلحة آخر في نفس الشركة.
This was a hard dependency that was not being met
وعملي يعتمد على هذه البيانات وحصولي عليها كان صعبًا،
despite many reminders to the stakeholder who was supposed to provide that data.
برغم من تذكير صاحب المصلحة أكثر من مرة بإمدادي بالبيانات تلك.
The business for surprisingly,
لم يقم العميل
not pushing the stakeholder to get that data to me and things kept getting delayed.
بالضغط على هذا الطرف الآخر لإعطائي البيانات وبدأت الأمور تتأخر.
Later on, I did get the data and implemented the module,
حصلت على البيانات لاحقًا وطبقت النموذج،
but it was way past the deadline.
لكني تجاوزت الموعد النهائي للتسليم.
When it was time for payment for that module,
وعندما حان الوقت لاستلام مستحقاتي المالية نظير النموذج،
the client was not very willing to make the payment in
لم يكن العميل راغبًا في دفع المبلغ
full and mentioned reasons like the delay caused in the delivery.
كاملًا وذكر أن السبب هو تأخير التسليم.
I knew that there were significant delays because of this
كنت أعلم أن التسليم تأخر كثيرًا بسبب
dependency not being fulfilled and not entirely because of the delays my end.
احتياجي للبيانات لإتمام النموذج ولم يكن التأخير بسببي أنا.
But this was not the time to lose my cool.
ولكن ليس هذا الوقت المناسب لأفقد هدوئي.
I approached the client and asked them to get on a call.
تواصلت مع العميل وطلبت منه أن يتصل بي تليفونيًا.
This is the time to take care of your relationship with the client and not get mad.
وهنا يجب أن تحافظ على علاقتك بالعميل ولا يجب أن تفقد هدوئك.
Believe me, I was mad from within.
صدقني، كنت أشعر بالجنون بداخلي.
But when I talked to the client,
ولكن عند التحدث مع العميل،
I tried to keep calm and focus on the main issue,
حاولت أن أكون هادئًا وأن أُركز على النقطة الأساسية،
and tried to point out reasons for delay to the client.
وحاولت الإشارة إلى أسباب التأخير.
I also gently asked if I could pause working
كما طلبت بلطف إن كان بإمكاني التوقف عن العمل
further on the project until this payment of this module is cleared.
لحين تسوية أمر تسديد المقابل المادي لهذا النموذج.
The discussion with the client helped clarify
ساعد النقاش مع العميل في توضيح الأمر
the disconnect and calm down the matters. Guess what?
وتهدئة الأمور، وتخيل ماذا حدث؟
The client agreed to make the payment in full,
وافق العميل على دفع المقابل المالي كاملًا
and also pause the project until the payment was cleared.
ووافق على إيقاف العمل حتى تسديد المبلغ.
Eventually, I decided not to pause the project and kept
وفي النهاية قررت عدم إيقاف العمل على المشروع وواصلت
going in good faith and the client paid me in full.
العمل بثقة، وسدد العميل مستحقاتي المالية كاملة.
In fact, the client went ahead and signed
في الواقع قام العميل بتوقيع
another contract with me for the next six months.
عقد عمل آخر معي لمدة ستة أشهر مقبلة.
This time, I could put my terms in the contract
هذه المرة وضعت شروطي في العقد بشأن
about the dependencies and how and when they should be fulfilled.
البيانات التابعة للمهمة ومتى ينبغي إمدادي بها.
Something like this did not happen again and did not affect my payments.
لم يحدث هذا الأمر مرة أخرى ولم يؤثر على مستحقاتي المالية.
Making sure that your communication is ethical,
إن التأكد من التواصل الأخلاقي اللائق
may not just help you traverse through a difficult situation better,
لن يساعدك فقط في اجتياز المواقف الصعبة،
it might end up winning the client for you.
ولكنه قد يجعلك تفوز بالعميل.
On the flip side,
وعلى الجانب الآخر،
when things go ory and the communication becomes unethical,
عندما تسوء الأمور ويصبح التواصل مع العميل غير لائق،
it starts getting deflected in the payment disputes,
يؤثر ذلك على النزاع على المستحقات المالية،
disagreements, and bad reviews which could adversely affect a freelancing career.
ويؤدي إلى خلافات ومراجعات سيئة قد تؤثر سلبًا على مجالك المهني في العمل الحر.
In short responding is way better than reacting.
باختصار، فإن الفعل أفضل من رد الفعل.